A Guide to the Samuel Milner National Airport Research Papers, 1800-1981
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Samuel Milner National Airport Research Papers, 1800-1981
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 13
17 boxes.
Milner, Dr. Samuel, 1910-2000
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Samuel Milner in 1985.
Historical Information
What is now known as Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport has changed in many ways over the years in both name and location since it first opened as Hoover Field in 1926. In 1928, a second airport, opposite Hoover Field, was opened called Washington Airport, and in 1933 the two combined to form Washington Hoover Airport (the present site of the Pentagon). In 1938, restrictions on federal development of airports were lifted, and President Roosevelt appropriated money for the creation of an up-to-date airport for the Washington area. National Airport opened in 1941, approximately one mile south of the 1920s sites, at its present location. In 1998, the airport's name was changed to Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport.
Scope and Content
Record Group 13 contains materials gathered, notes taken, and personal research done by Dr. Samuel Milner for a history he hoped to publish on Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport (Reagan National Airport) while he was on the Historical Staff of the Federal Aviation Administration.
This collection covers the years 1800 1981, with the bulk dates falling between 1910 1941, and it measures 7.1 linear feet. The research in this collection focuses on the history of the property that is now Reagan National Airport, going back to colonial times. However, there are interviews and articles that deal with airplanes and early aviation, and the development and construction of Reagan National Airport as well.
Series 1, Research Notes, contain mostly handwritten transcripts of articles from local newspapers, including The Daily News, The Washington Herald, The Washington Post, and The Evening Star, and aviation magazines. There are also some photocopies of articles, especially in the folders with material dated after 1920. Series 2, Aviation and Airport Subject Files, has folders on various airport related topics from many sources including federal agencies and reports on hearings both Congressional and local. Milner interviewed several prominent people involved with Washington's early aviation era, and his notes and transcripts are contained in Series 5, Interview Notes and Transcripts. These interviews were done in both 1972-1973 and 1979-1981.
There are 71 photographs in Series 6, Photographs; most of them are reproductions from various historical collections in the Washington area such as the National Archives and the Library of Congress. Series 7, Published Material, contains original and photocopied portions of pre published histories and reports on the airport and aviation in general. Included in this series is a report regarding purchasing of a stretch of what is then called Military Road to use for airport purposes; this report includes maps and photographs.
Arrangement
RG 13 is divided into seven series; the first three contain research notes on various topics written by Milner. Series 1, Research Notes, are Milner's notes filed chronologically. Series 2, Aviation and Airport Subject Files and Series 3, Local History Materials from Various Sources are subject files on Reagan National Airport and local history, filed alphabetically by subject. Series 5, Interview Notes and Transcripts contains Milner's notes and transcripts of his interviews with various aviation personalities filed alphabetically by name of the interview subject. The folders in Series 7, Published Material, have quotes around original titles of the folders; these refer to folders containing photocopies of publications about a particular subject.
Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name. Folders with oversized materials have a double asterisk [**] to denote where material was removed and separation sheets added.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
For more information on Reagan National Airport and other Washington-area airports, see RG 37, Metropolitan Washington Airports, and RG 189, Anderson National Airport Collection.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Washington National Airport; Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport.; Washington-Hoover Airport; Airports.; Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Research Notes on National Airport and Predecessors
  - 1800 (Box 1)
  - 1801 (1) (Box 1)
  - 1801 (2) (Box 1)
  - 1836 (Box 1)
  - 1850 (Box 1)
  - 1852 (Box 1)
  - 1854 (Box 1)
  - 1855 (Box 1)
  - 1856 (Box 1)
  - 1857 (Box 1)
  - 1858 (Box 1)
  - 1859 (Box 1)
  - 1860 (Box 1)
  - 1861 (Box 1)
  - 1862 (Box 1)
  - 1873-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1887-1889 (Box 1)
  - 1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891 (Box 1)
  - 1892 (Box 2)
  - 1893 (Box 2)
  - 1894 (Box 2)
  - 1895 (1) (Box 2)
  - 1895 (2) (Box 2)
  - 1896 (Box 2)
  - 1897 (Box 2)
  - 1898 (Box 2)
  - 1899 (Box 2)
  - 1900 (Box 2)
  - 1901 (Box 2)
  - 1902 (Box 2)
  - 1903 (Box 2)
  - 1904 (Box 3)
  - 1905 (Box 3)
  - 1906 (Box 3)
  - 1907 (Box 3)
  - 1908 (Box 3)
  - 1909 (Box 3)
  - 1910 (Box 3)
  - 1911 (Box 3)
  - 1912 (Box 3)
  - 1913 (Box 3)
  - 1914 (Box 3)
  - 1915 (Box 3)
  - 1916 (Box 4)
  - 1917 (Box 4)
  - 1918 (Box 4)
  - 1919 (Box 4)
  - 1920 (Box 4)
  - 1921 (Box 4)
  - 1922 (Box 4)
  - 1923 (Box 4)
  - 1924 (Box 4)
  - 1925 (Box 4)
  - 1926 (Box 4)
  - 1927 (1) (Box 4)
  - 1927 (2) (Box 4)
  - 1927 (3) (Box 4)
  - 1927 (4) (Box 5)
  - 1927 (5) (Box 5)
  - 1927 (6) (Box 5)
  - 1928 (1) (Box 5)
  - 1928 (2) (Box 5)
  - 1928 (3) (Box 5)
  - 1928 (4) (Box 5)
  - 1928 (5) (Box 5)
  - January-February 1929 (Box 5)
  - March 1929 (Box 5)
  - April 1929 (Box 6)
  - May 1929 (Box 6)
  - June 1929 (Box 6)
  - July 1929 (Box 6)
  - August-September 1929 (Box 6)
  - October-December 1929 (Box 6)
  - Airport Hearings, 1929 (Box 6)
  - January-February 1930 (Box 6)
  - March 1930 (Box 6)
  - April-May 1930 (Box 6)
  - June-July 1930 (Box 7)
  - August-September 1930 (Box 7)
  - October-November 1930 (Box 7)
  - 1931 (Box 7)
  - 1932 (Box 7)
  - January 1933 (Box 7)
  - February-May 1933 (Box 7)
  - June-July 1933 (Box 7)
  - August-September 1933 (Box 7)
  - October-November 1933 (Box 7)
  - Airport Hearings, 1933 (Box 7)
  - January 1934 (Box 8)
  - February-July 1934 (Box 8)
  - September-December 1934 (Box 8)
  - January 1935 (Box 8)
  - March-April 1935 (Box 8)
  - May-June 1935 (Box 8)
  - July 1935 (Box 8)
  - August-December 1935 (Box 8)
  - Airport Hearings, 1935 (1) (Box 8)
  - Airport Hearings, 1935 (2) (Box 8)
  - January-February 1936 (1) (Box 9)
  - January-February 1936 (2) (Box 9)
  - March 1936 (Box 9)
  - April-June 1936 (Box 9)
  - July-December 1936 (Box 9)
  - January-July 1937 (Box 9)
  - July 1937 (Box 9)
  - August 1937 (Box 9)
  - September 1937 (Box 9)
  - October-December 1937 (Box 10)
  - January-March 1938 (Box 10)
  - April-June 1938 (Box 10)
  - July-September 1938 (Box 10)
  - October 1938 (Box 10)
  - November-December 1938 (Box 10)
  - Airport Hearings, 1938 (1) (Box 10)
  - Airport Hearings, 1938 (2) (Box 10)
  - January-May 1939 (Box 10)
  - June-September 1939 (Box 10)
  - October-December 1939 (Box 10)
  - January-March 1940 (Box 11)
  - April-August 1940 (Box 11)
  - September 1940 (Box 11)
  - October-December 1940 (Box 11)
  - January-May 1941 (Box 11)
  - June 1941 (Box 11)
  - July 1941 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Clippings, Maps (Box 11)
- Aviation and Airport Subject Files
  - Airline Schedules, 1929 (Box 11)
  - Airports, Miscellaneous, 1940-1976 (Box 11)
  - Benning Race Track, 1875-1921 (Box 11)
  - Biographies - Beachey, Lincoln, 1887-1929 (Box 11)
  - Biographies - Bertrandias, Victor E., 1894-1961 (Box 11)
  - Biographies - Dulany, H. Rozier, 1858-1940 (Box 11)
  - Biographies - Emil, Henry & the Berliner Helicopter, 1895-1940 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Fahy, Herb, 1900-1935 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Fokker, Anthony, 1920-1929 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Hambleton, John A., 1918-1929 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Musick, Edwin C., 1935 1935-1938 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Parker, A., 1895-1942 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Pickup, Christopher V., 1917-1935 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Tipton, Col. William D. 1920-1957 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Wentworth, Ralph, 1920-1957 (Box 12)
  - Biographies - Young, Clarence, 1889-1929 (Box 12)
  - Bolling Field, Anacostia, 1891-1933 (Box 12)
  - Boundary Cases, 1749-1921 (Box 12)
  - Brick Manufacturing, 1901-1970s (Box 12)
  - College Park Airport, 1909-1976 (Box 12)
  - Florida Airways - St. Petersburg, 1924-1927 (Box 12)
  - Ford Tri Motor, 1926-1940 (Box 12)
  - Hybla Valley & Thousand Acre Airport, 1900-1980 (Box 12)
  - Impact Items, 1924-1935 (Box 12)
  - Langley, Dr., Flying Machine, 1903 (Box 12)
  - Navy Radio Towers, 1912-1941 (Box 12)
  - North American Aerial Transportation Company, 1921 (Box 12)
  - Pennsylvania Rapid Transit (PRT), 1926-1927 (1) (Box 12)
  - Pennsylvania Rapid Transit (PRT), 1926-1927 (2) (Box 12)
  - Ryan Airlines, 1921-1925 (Box 13)
  - Summary of Congressional Bills, 1927-1938 (Box 13)
  - Washington Hoover/National Airport, 1926-1941 (Box 13)
  - Washington Hoover Airport, 1926-1944 (1) (Box 13)
  - Washington Hoover Airport, 1926-1944 (2) (Box 13)
  - Washington National Airport (WNA), 1940-1966 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Brochure, 1941 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Development, Articles, 1933 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Engineering Articles, Pentagon, 1940-1980 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Legal Jurisdiction Problem, 1926-1971 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Military Engineers Articles, 1939-1941 (Box 13)
  - WNA, Naming, 1940 (Box 13)
- Local History Materials from Various Sources
  - Alexandria County, 1789-1916 (Box 13)
  - Arlington Farms, 1796-1953 (Box 13)
  - Arlington History, 1773-1917 (1) (Box 13)
  - Arlington History, 1773-1917 (2) (Box 14)
  - Arlington Miscellaneous, to 1891 (Box 14)
  - Civil War, Freedmen's Village, 1861-1890 (Box 14)
  - East Potomac Park, 1870-1920 (Box 14)
  - Garfield, James A., 1870-1871 (Box 14)
  - Housing Patent, 1669 (Box 14)
  - Jackson City, 1836-1957 (Box 14)
  - Long Bridge, 1809-1901 (1) (Box 14)
  - Long Bridge, 1809-1901 (2) (Box 14)
  - Luna Park, 1906-1913 (1) (Box 14)
  - Luna Park, 1906-1913 (2) (Box 14)
  - Luna Park, Photocopied Images, 1906 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Local History, 1606-1940 (Box 14)
  - Noyes, Crosby S., 1825-1908 (Box 14)
  - Potomac, 1924 (Box 14)
  - Potomac Fisheries, 1768-1921 (Box 14)
  - Potomac Region History, 1589-1938 (Box 14)
  - Potomac Yards, 1669-1980 (Box 14)
  - Spanish at Occoquan, 1570-1907 (Box 14)
  - Washington D.C. History, 1789-1875 (Box 15)
- Milner Manuscripts and Articles
  - A Pioneer Airline Shows Its Colors, 1975 (Box 15)
  - Dulles Retrospective, 1982 (Box 15)
- Interview Notes and Transcripts
  - Boudwin, Joseph E., 1980 (Box 15)
  - Fahy, Herbert; Margaret Fahy Raynor, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Funkhauser, Robert E., 1973 (Box 15)
  - Musser, Phyllis; Fredericksburg Potomac RR, 1979 (Box 15)
  - Priester, Andre, 1981 (Box 15)
  - Reiss, Stewart A., 1973 (Box 15)
  - Solomon, Samuel J., 1972 (Box 15)
  - Steinhauer, J. Earl, 1973-79 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous Interviews, 1979 (Box 15)
- Photographs
  - Hoover Field* (Box 15)
  - Experimental Farm* (Box 15)
  - National Airport* (Box 15)
  - Oversize** (Box 15)
- Published Material
  - "DC Area" (Box 16)
  - "Columbia Historical Society" (Box 16)
  - "DC-Virginia" (Box 16)
  - "Washington Family" (Box 16)
  - "Virginia" (1) (Box 16)
  - "Arlington Co." (Box 16)
  - "Virginia" (Box 16)
  - "Capt. John Smith" (Box 16)
  - "Custis-Lee, Alexandria, Analostan Island" (Box 16)
  - "Miscellaneous" (Box 16)
  - Voyages into Airy Regions, John F. R. Scott Jr. (Box 17)
  - Take Off at Mid-Century, Stuart Rochester (Box 17)
  - Turbulence Aloft, John R. M. Wilson (Box 17)
  - FAA Historical Fact Book: A Chronology, 1926-1971 (Box 17)
  - Report, Proposal for Arlington's Purchase of Military Road, 1937 (Box 17)
  - Report, Proposal for Arlington's Purchase of Military Road, 1937, Photographs* (Box 17)
  - Report, Proposal for Arlington's Purchase of Military Road, 1937, Maps** (Box 17)
  - Samuel Milner Obituary, 2000 (Box 17)